all right let's do some memory and then
we'll do questions and answers okay that
calcula gimmicky can be like any key on
did you like in Manila whether or not
you have refuge within your heart
depends on whether or not you have
refugee in your heart that's what it
says basic enjoy Cleveland has succulent
can do more good nama do you know my kid
back then Don Ameche pond so there's a
tradition in Tibet that people will go
on and retreat and try to collect a
hundred thousand eleven hundred thousand
frustrations hundred thousand going
through a successor it's okay if you
want to do that but it's more important
that you feel refuge in your heart by
refusing to answer someone who hurt you
right okay darling our digital or so
till a million beseech you like your
thumbs up they're gonna so you have to
make efforts to seek refuge and not talk
references okay
sing Crescent I'm not chakras then I'm
suited I do think quite a lot make me
now we talked about a little bit about
this the other day really good debate
and here it comes those of you making
their own and Adam and Katie when when
we were talking about cause message and
result message okay day long singular
good scene so you can go to refuge - for
example Buddha which somebody else
already achieved like Gautama Buddha
okay you can take
in the buddha who already reached
Buddhahood okay that's called good
Kendall moves cause refuge okay it's
actually as a cost in you to become a
Buddha okay good
kendo some ball that's called simple
refuge thank you bye ginger tea quenches
I mean me they meet ups are targeted
Kendall kept on keep on
that's called normal reactions and
special taking refuge is to try to
connect with the Buddha that you will
become and take refuge in Buddha who is
chair to come okay and the other side is
a very sweet practice to talk to
yourself huge abouna because future
Buddha can see you
Nancy you have an awesome Buddha can see
you right now
so sometimes I just like to say hi okay
and your future Buddha is watching you
now okay you're probably asking you
hurry up okay listen this agenda agenda
very huge change then there's a
different level for each London
practitioner who takes refuge evaluation
chamber to some shape or not ECAM
doorkeeper Jamie night or bigger key
kendo chairman on Omnitech
Tammy Tata you helped I came back and
became dealt and kept imagining Iike
some cheaper conduct much okay no money
he said the difference between the way
untrained people take refuge and the way
that trained people take refuge so he's
talking here about tell Park in Port
Gamble means like some old person who
never got training on refuge and they
will
you know go to the temple and and make
incense and say I take refuge like that
but they don't understand how to fool
refuge so think refuges the problems I
see our colors from me and I can change
them okay that's really okay
like your husband change em only shake
em giggles I reckon Arizona morning
built it so soon come on Miss a Burmese
people who didn't get trained properly
Buddhists who didn't get trained
properly you know so we're gonna go to
London junkie
they can have this emotion that I put
all my trust in Buddha for the two
reasons okay there are two reasons for
refuge very famous what are they number
one yeah it's like you know I grew up
with three brothers no sisters we had a
lot of you know punching going on from
time to time and yeah my brother would
hit me okay that's the first cause of
refuge is pain and second cause of
refuges to these things there's someone
who can help you so we've run into you
know our mom's room and said mommy he
hit me okay so those are two causes of
taking refuge you have a problem and we
have someone you think who can help you
mommy will go to help brother not to do
that dance animal attacking men I
remember their nail not a turtle or not
so when somebody sick and they go
through a doctor and they try to take
medicine and they trust the nurses it
put their trust in those three things
doctors medicine and nurses know
included are too much into today we have
to think like them doing family going
liudmila kelvin are we have to make sure
we understand why taking refuge number
one understand the problems you have
even if you don't have any problems now
you're alive and we won't be for long
doesn't I think that's already a problem
do you know if your problem even if you
don't did you have any problems you have
a problem okay the moment you're alive
was getting old the moment is getting
all you're going to lose this body and
then where you're going to go after that
we don't know okay and this body is very
weak and hard to keep alive Kajal I mean
yellow color caldo unlucky like a pie
and a daily so Taylor
secondly I think that the Buddha can
help me monocular kid like they need to
charity most important is to trust that
reference they'll encounter and sit down
salt down then if you don't understand
the concept of reference in the sense of
the Anthony then 60 tons of tea in if
you say a million times I go for refuge
Transylvanians indicates a way see our
magenta rings indicate area even if you
think you're a pretty powerful
Bodhisattva or a pretty powerful Tonto
car if you don't have resins in your
heart then it's not going to work okay
God does remain calm especially the
early kenapa mama said
maintain Shalimar supona double numbers
and eh I'll do my HSC much enjoyment
okay here's that famous quotation okay I
taught you all the ideas
now I just want you been here from
Scripture okay Nathan means Abbot elder
like the sixteen yards and shell is
honorifics or face Marsh pickings he's
looking down on us the abbot is looking
down from his term she's built a lot but
Dajjal numbers are gay but he didn't
become a Buddhist yet we're hoping he
will
okay the abbot of the monastery of one
of the big Mother's Day nearly ten
thousand months he was his a British yet
but we hope you'll become one maybe okay
it's an old joke okay she became chances
all right cannula
these are the benefits of taking refuge
I put them at the end of your debate she
okay so when do we debate tomorrow must
be something for debating tonight in
there Kevin but here are some of the
classic eight benefits for taking refuge
okay
they're not all of them are your debate
sheet or most of them are okay number
one number son gave a clipper if you any
person who refuses to answer another
person who criticizes them because they
understand that the person is
criticizing them because they answered
last time okay then that person became a
Buddhist and I like to see seven
thousand people came to DCI programs the
last tour two weeks you know if they
understood about these they're Buddhist
it doesn't matter what they think they
are doesn't matter there
okay that's cool okay that's number one
number two you need to take refuge in
order to have Buddhist vows
you can't take lifetime vows you can't
take ten commitments you can't take
monks mouth nuns vows
buddy stop without counting vowels you
can't take any of them if you haven't
taken refuge okay
and if you don't understand what it is
then we can't your your body won't hold
the other vows okay number two number
three wasn't stuck they naked dippin I'm
say forgive my old bad karma that you
did our we call it disabled by your
current understanding it cannot open
okay they will just sit there in your
mind stay forever and they will never
open
they are said by not understanding see
yeah that's true we call stock may give
us a together such many children start
to suffer members of the digital
starting country didn't our southern
Kentucky because I'm a monkey terminal
until machine and seniority member
technical to me again I'm in comedy
below that's the verse of the double
crochet gave us a Chilean sir good thing
to do bye-bye without understanding what
you doing and then those big promise
we're out and then this become as you do
with understanding generally promise
that you good ones that you do that you
appreciate growth good comments that you
do apparently and you don't you know
very selfish is okay
there's a beautiful debate in the
beginning of the module macabre tire
where China Jackie asked the question
well well a good deed done by a selfish
person works will it have a result and
the answer is yeah it will but then the
comment about motivation will catch up
with that muscle okay so that's affirm
this question but uh generally the two
things
anger can short-circuit I've seen a good
scene and misunderstanding can
short-circuit
but a good scene and understanding can
short-circuit a bad seed like when we do
the four cars
is that okay they did you get did I miss
oh yeah I understand why isn't the
process the same between good sings and
dances yeah that's a good question
[Music]
God seeds get hurt by understanding good
seeds get hurt by misunderstanding okay
number one when you take refuge and me
do something good it gets stronger it's
more powerful he says he adds the word
de la Coeur de la fille means you don't
have to put a lot of effort into it if
you do good beings trying to do the four
steps it works faster and easier okay
number five we got me my Yuki met day we
took by things that other people try to
do to hurt you and things that spirits
try to do to hurt you don't touch you
they don't reach you okay that's number
five number six we attended your songs
in the door you will not go to the lower
realms after you back number seven
makeup done totally gentle Giovannetti
Juba all of your dreams rather short
term like financial security or long
terms like reaching enlightenment you
can reach effortless effortlessly they
make okay and then number eight we
return yeah you'll become a bit of
faster you reach enlightenment fastest
now he's going to explain those a in
more detail
okay very good loose bark and I'll go so
while we're doing pretty well nothing
well well go for a while then we'll take
questions and date I came to she had got
shanking memo table cards on them then
he says you know like a year in Thailand
honey there was 400 students in the
class in the retreat in he announced
that we're going to get very few cows
and everybody got excited
and the ones that didn't get excited
felt pressure to do it anyway because
everybody else is saying and that's
called limits um
in Tibetan if you're interested lamo not
dilate more means we call it following
the crowd okay following the crowd
[Music]
telecom don't do that - tell me about
don't just say that refuge words many
top and they kept some things believe
that there's some danger ahead of you
and really really ask them to help you
as ask the Buddhist country Camden on
rocky magnum camp on that if you take
refuge properly my dear husband in the
kitchen numbers I gave myself we become
a Buddhist and Jain Mehta if you don't
understand that process
Campbell Boone thought and even if you
do the refuge prayer a hundred thousand
times which is a custom number mature it
doesn't make you a Buddhist it won't
make you a Buddhist then come door so
good sir when they do like Yaga second
good he says yeah
nowadays you hear people say I gotta go
collect we use a rosin me and we say I'm
going to do the Dharma Sangha Buddha
Dharma Sangha within a second and we
when people say I got a connected on my
resume but you're doing head and today I
got it collected in my heart okay
I have to collect it in my heart nard
Abigail and art I say there was a a
Muslim ought are some optical duxelles
Dowell je t'aime no sir this is the
famous story there was a guy named art
irony went with a couple of other guys
to like a case and they all took their
rosaries and they wanted to see how many
message press they could collect in like
a week okay then autarky gendered in the
north on blackboard coordination then
Akhtar made a mistake he did them slow
and he thought about it okay they
sucked they really were then his friends
finished their 100,000 like two days
before he did and they got irritated
with him because they had to wait for
him saying that weekender sit down so
perceived a much here a joke by Tuesday
the others finished faster because they
were in trying to think about what they
were saying
boom test seemed to nil enough and when
they were close to finishing 100,000
closer autarky Tom Malone told me they
got tokpah
here is a useful where that means
suspicious or paranoid or schizophrenic
and here it means they had a suspicion
that our tire was too slow with being
too slow my loan for mangy council and
they asked him how many how many
are you up to because they didn't want
to wait for him
italki kids Jumbo chaga so came here
down said well he said are you just
trying to reach a number is that all
we're doing here you know he criticized
his friends he said I would just kind of
meet your number 7:30 I'm gonna make
such jokes in sorry it's okay sit dear
100,000 but as you do it you have to
imagine taking real refuge in the
kitchen okay
in some ways I know that three-year
retreatants who will agree clearly
treats a little bit of a pretty color
you feel like you don't have all the
opportunities you have in the outside
world to take refuse because no one's
irritating you quite at that frequency
level except for spiders and stuff so
sometimes I miss people or when I'm in
retreat because I can't make such good
karma okay Kendall made by coming to us
on the memo if you think about
what you're saying and it amazing okay
number two redaction foundations for all
yourselves don't some Khon Kaen Lancome
whether you take part in motion cells
body south of elves or secret sauce
Kendall somebody asked me the other day
would you like me to come teach Tantra
to your students you know and I'm like
okay it's like you don't have time time
you know we spent how many years 7 years
doing turn turn and we translated 10,000
pages of content but we didn't show it
to anybody okay
because tanto means secret you know and
no I don't need someone to teach my
students secret
okay I can picture the jerky game a part
of me okay we can't walk so do you take
no matter which vows you want to take
come don't irritate it always starts
from taking refuge Percodan member
mikela but if you don't have refuge in
each other take vows they don't grow
inside of you
[Music]
they're less I see me curtains and local
tissue not sell soap your opinion but
then I gave you this meditation with a
fruit tree and the idea is taking
refugees like that nutrients in the soil
and then your vows are like tree and the
fruits of your vows are keeping your
mouth and when the fruits of your vows
grow there's always a little refuge are
in them and so if you don't have that
kind of fertilizer in the soil there
won't be fruits they won't grow okay in
right there you have to add a gypsum and
Epsom salts and recall that stuff well a
biochar but anyway okay we can't win
especially Kum Kee so that the earth is
the foundation of all houses of all
crops of all trees of forests etc
pyridinium Betar it's like the who said
that Lenin's
or marks the earth is the source of all
well the soil is the source of all
wealth ultimately everything comes down
to the cell and part Kimberley Dahme
become tthe thing and ultimately all
vows come down to refuge okay like the
soil all right then
number three all bad comments you made
are cleared away come though you know
once i can- our mumblety-peg album my
kid days
Rangi up zucchini but tell me over there
below but don't tell me what to tell me
some men not to me some may not yeah
five immediately if you if you just five
things that you do then we go straight
to hell after you die first one kill
your mother kill your father kill and
then draw blood from a Buddha in in
English okay not as a nurse what's this
next one yeah
take the Sun guy with the single
Kimberly magnet something they could
give on mobile today so he gives the
example of a famous Prince named
ajatashatru odd just a means not born
yet cetera means enemy and somebody told
his father your son is going to kill you
he's your unborn enemy when his wife got
pregnant this this what he call it she
said said their son's going to kill you
when he grows up but still she wanted to
have the same right so his name was
unborn enemy age etc and then he killed
his father who was a cameo with the gym
you just before our heart don't have to
come back nominee Turner
just before I killed his father who's
been Basara yeah he sent the wheel of
life to the other king what's the other
Kings mean yeah it was Anna which is
probably router on earth thing anyway
okay
Kenny on the other topic told darlings
he murdered him his father and so he
committed some people like that merely
some Manship are circular comes with so
many Big Dipper channel and even if
there's five deeds you can do that are
close to that and he said if you take
good Russians in the Buddha you can
purify this son you can send some jilted
are sure to get built up with how they
lock non-governmental ticket jump even
if you just repeat the name of the
Buddha or your teacher of course or you
repeat one of the professional wisdom
sutras like the diamond cutter or the
Heart Sutra to contain sentence hanging
couple moment of the jump many eons of
bad karma sorry rekt don't Dana opinion
Yun Yun's of authority it's said in the
citrus many times do you want to know
what the five close ones are I went and
got it for you oh man stop my computer's
cranky Johnson misses a many percent on
you a minion so the five close ones are
close to the five real ones they have a
what he called simple sympathy
sympathetic they're sympathetic said huh
okay try some you may sit and they to
kill to killer of Bodhisattva who is
close to reaching the goal if similar to
killing you
okay I'm about to tell you I went and
looked it up defined as a bodhisattva
who hasn't seen the emptiness directly
yet but who is going to become a Buddha
within a hundred yawns I'm saying if a
body suffer hasn't seen any misdirecting
yet but he will become a Buddha within a
hundred yards or less to kill that one
is called a closed class one of the
closest close to the main part
so there's five some eight and there's
five close ones okay so that's supposed
to be similar to killing your father
datian do
Madhava MA - ma long youngest Angela if
your mother is in our heart and you rape
her that's close to killing your mother
so it's not as it's close okay got it
pretty bad things number two
low Pop Tart Makeba septum--ah if you
kill a person who seems emptiness but
who hasn't reached Nirvana yet it's
close to killing in our heart okay
chipton Shivani to destroy a temple or a
suture a stupa out of anger
datian she said cool any integrity
torturer is close to what yeah I think
taking the British blood out of fingers
okay
make you a bit of lead on a minger only
one person has ever done it by the way
can you be sure to do a gotalk now this
is serious one to miss appropriate
Sangha money to miss appropriate Sangha
money not to keep your finances
carefully thank God we have Rob Russell
ger otherwise we'd probably do it a
million times
okay what's that cluster splitting the
dumber okay so it's like stealing things
from the Sun guy using things from
Diamond Mountain that you didn't ask
permission things like that so you got
to be super careful around Tsongas
possessions it's very easy to break
that's the only one that would be easy
for us to break you know so you have to
be cut up anal about it okay careful
about it be super careful about it son
death possessions okay number four you
make great piles of good karma by the
way we're going to go for another half
hour so parts of different like young
the short version of the perfection of
wisdom Sutra says capsules cinema took
me 16 becomes India nerditude and we had
this before if the good karma you make
from taking refuge properly took form
since ago form it wouldn't fit inside
this universe okay I I was in the high
school and we had a really cool
principal and one day he he made all the
students go to the football stadium and
we all sat there and then he said let me
show you something
and he started he drove a car onto the
football field and he put some chemical
in the carburetor
that made all the pollution turn into
like a red cloud and it filled the
football stadium
two minutes and we were all alike
because because you can't see carbon
monoxide you see and if you could see it
you'd go crazy you freaked out you said
nobody should drive any cars we must
look everywhere you know so the good
karma of taking refuge if you took if
you made smoke out of it recover the
whole planet
it's huge ok all right chef a dark and
dirty opinion does in a park in malaria
there's lots of things in Buddhism that
are not measurable not even thinkable
we're going to get to a part in the
diamond cutter scooter don't come unless
you know where he says so pretty says
tell me how much good karma you guys
from my stunning the diamond cutter and
what it looks at I mean it says do you
value your sanity you know you want me
to make you crazy
you want to go to the mental side I mean
somebody but that's okay you can tell me
some other time if I told you how much
good karma you made from studying the
diamond kind of you is going say it's
very interesting in combination has a
long description of mental illnesses
that you can get from China imagine how
much you can come ok so I said a machine
camera can become way elected because I
come on my back in my sink I'm so gentle
thank you to me about your day here is a
place in the scriptures where you get
sort of a confirmation one for Karma's
that are done without strong intention
but are extremely powerful because of
the object okay so you can do something
flippant towards your heart MoMA not
very serious
without much intention but they are so
powerful for you there are such a
powerful car
for you that it still becomes very
serious okay
so that also means you know if you make
a cup of tea for your heart mama and
you're lazy and you don't make it very
well
you still like go to paradise for ten
thousand years or something okay I'm
going okay
so there are certain cases where certain
objects are so powerful so just thinking
about Bruna when you take reference it's
very powerful even if your motivation is
not very strong it just the power of the
object okay it's in canto gentle figure
and therefore it will without question
become a cause for you to reach
enlightenment okay even if your
motivation was lousy
Minjae pay my carpet darling we did this
part already this is the Lotus Sutra and
Lord Buddha is something something very
similar to our Jesus said about Easter
he says when he said if the soil is
fertile and if there's no stone and if
you plant a seed and you water it and
you don't want it to grow it's still
going to grow okay
you can't stop it so if you even just
think about the Buddha the Karma is so
powerful that you will get enlightened
very quickly just daydreaming about the
brew okay even if you don't want to
become a winner you will have to be a
good okay all right I'm gonna skip the
rest that bike as we come in it
got self activity devil may invade unum
do you think that the fruit the apple
that grows on a tree after you plant an
apple scene and it grows into a tree
do you think that if you don't want it
it's going to become not an apple listen
let me do from silver jumping in my life
so no I think it was still being at work
okay they worship a mother
Catawba Anandi even if you're a person
who is all caught up in some time you
know all day long trying to get money
trying to buy new clothes get your new
Maserati okay certain simple Ogawa and
that's all you want but if you
accidentally make an offering to a
Buddha it's and then you say I don't
want to be enlightened I don't want to
reach nirvana you still got a recently
runner
okay got it very powerful object and I
mean given me a minute Meimei by the way
here no place like Matt means it means
utter impossibility okay it's completely
impossible
[Music]
go cut make it come go Sonia like you
can carry teller did I mean good come
even if you don't want it a nun under
you will reach the burner I say you know
if anyone asks you who says it I said so
okay the last thing Buddha says I said
so I say so okay okay okay Sarge it's
under Sun it's on the damn lock sent to
kick back a root cellar kid like there
are times a day one element there for
unity come on young and a paper partner
then he repeats himself and says any
good cover you may
thinking about the Buddha will make you
reach nirvana and nobody can stop it two
more hang in there okay
or I already told you that one if you
take lessons you cannot be touched by
spirits or humans who want to hurt you
and we talked about our demon with that
rope we talked about all of those I
don't know why we talked about he talked
about another ping Donna you talked
about the bridge where the demons
couldn't get by he talked about the
theater said I'm glad there's no more
than three runway killer to magic dog
nature part and we talked about that oh
let me go and over the platypus
yeah we finished that yeah we finished
yes finished and okay miss minor let's
do a little bit more okay you okay you
were hoping for the popcorn at the
ginseng we're up to Joe chin Jo B or C
atm
there you go yep George every gender Don
langar khana mention was Sidney and
Tembe
same month then Lord our teacher who
helped bring Buddhism to Tibet he
considered refuge and the teachings on
karma to be so important he almost
didn't teach anything else okay I had a
I was watching the sitar teacher online
there are maybe a couple hundred
standard Roget
and his advice was he said he had only
mastered two so far and he's like 80 in
his life only two songs he had mastered
and it's like that
Ayesha only mastered two subjects karma
and taking refuge and people used to
call him
venerable Russia's decided not to call
him a dishonest and it's going to call
you mr. refuge do you know it's God's
secret name
[Music]
it's called including shavasana it means
when we say way to do we're going to do
yoga for an hour and he says including
savasana name is including Shannara all
right
not my lame day and then other people
called him varible karma dannyandkaren
Montessori because we only talked about
karma and taking refuge so what you did
to Joe said that he heard him he heard
about this joke people calling him mr.
karma or mr. refuge and it said even my
main house to teaching day my Ricci got
locked in mackelway kids all go away
so he says when you get to the day of
your death
don't try to remember some good Catholic
thing that you didn't practice very well
in your life
did not you got to teaching you didn't
practice and now you're dying don't
don't try to do it give it up just take
refuge that's better
Camden on blockchain just take a good
rest
Jay took money and sent me to my touch
opinion day then it's decided foregone
conclusion that you cannot be born into
the lower realms okay Sunday monkey show
me there's a place in tobacco one this
person llamas name was Sunday Winton
teacher from ones and he's very early
Donahue Anita dark you know Martina
Sardu Thomas obtained
cured you like irritants can do chicken
Sabine donuts you Amitabha if you have
not spent time doing just meditations do
remember with just meditations
okay at the end of your book okay he
says if you haven't done your death
meditations doctor you know marking that
then you decided you're getting you know
you're on your death I said oh I'm gonna
do glia Samantha I'm going
I need something powerful you know I'm
going to do tension on my birthday nice
update me sup means it won't help okay
she would get luckily chest if you if
you're gonna die suddenly if you get in
a car accident or something there was a
couple people who last time in Mertens
one of them hit a cows on this road you
have to be careful and he broke he broke
all the bones here
do you remember did you go through that
place with the big rocks halfway to
Tucson another lady her car fell off and
went down you know in Texas Canyon
David stump flipped his truck on the
dirt road here so I mean three people
have almost died going home from the
tree got it understand if suddenly
you're sitting there in Texas Canyon
with the car on top of you take refuge
with a dumbass on the Buddha Thomas and
a Brad I'm sorry okay then at least
you'd be born where there's lots of
pearls okay
jisub's with a top contender let's not
make chunks and blood Ellie
son do big tough guy if you want a
method for getting your hopes video a
wishes fulfilling a recent wishes come
true
Kendall they help me there's nothing
better than taking message then there
was a bodhisattva named rod my rod ding
is a famous monastery
some cop wrote a lamentable okay founded
by John Tintin thing yeah right there a
gentle cop and we'll look I'm sorry he
was a disciple of Justin copper somebody
translated the Iranian some translation
of this book he wasn't a student of
thought somebody said that he was
extremely some couple and he was born
the same year negation is syndicated in
and then he said mullah Mohammed a
solace Allah taught that I guess it was
a when he called a same into that like a
stitch in time saves nine
it was a saying in Tibet Milano much a
don't have much hoping in people ask the
gods for what you need okay
suet are when you forget samba ducky
Megaton took advantage and a sarcolemma
suicide may Cuba if you're hoping like
for a new job or you want your business
to do better next year or you want your
husband to Russia this is next year then
take wrestling's and strange dreams come
true if you don't want if you want your
wife to watch edition you can do the
same thing okay
nothing to mentally come to the South
County latina Gallatin Denis Johnson
stories one guy had a lawsuit it's
called come true and he took refuge and
he wonder was it murder site no a yard
and also as you want to just get
enlightened dr. Kim the general optimism
you think Deborah Center can continue no
matter what that thing happens in your
life if you're immediately can correct
news if you get used to taking refuge
there when you have a problem it will
come up in your knife mind about the
second husband okay going to did you
enjoy to medium bay so generally
whatever you think about a lot comes up
in your mind when you have a problem no
because on the day disjoint Union butt
cheek are you on Sundays is a demo so
two days so if you happen to get in an
accident you're dying try to take rest
don't do anything to mm what's that
suture didn't see the double somebody
Roger yeah it's the source of meditation
instruction that commercial against for
example in his yes grab some stuff some
meditation would you guys finished in
the first come over sooner you you did
it too fast and they can Galilean
irritate them China surround yourself
with images of the burner put them on
your here heater right so coupling here
I think of salary days you got monsters
all over her sorry
good idea I can't drain the month
because there is purely hot hot running
okay now it's my fault I said done
yesterday yes you minute - one
can try to remember the burner think
about the Brita from time to time stop
by J September container things that you
think about on a regular basis they'll
essentially up to W your mind goes to
them automatically when you have a
problem okay lay down Arthur get on Tom
are you talking I'm talking not but
chick then once in a while just say out
loud in your house when nobody's there
oh good oh you're so cool okay seriously
I'm not kidding like go take a walk in
time mountains just down nobody is the
cooler and they really like it because
it means you believe them you believe
they can hear you they like it okay
everyone swell due to driving in your
car and you get stuck at the Holland
Tunnel
you say they're gonna lose their cool
you know instead of sitting there like
this you know by the way you sometimes
you know they really like it when you do
stupid stuff like that
who does that except with a really good
British no just blurt out good a rental
car you know talk to them they can hear
you okay the world will think you're
crazy and the Buddha's will think you're
enlightened which is better okay
don't do it in the store
instead they're just a normal tone and
then you never know you might run into
Buddha's okay
you might relieve the Buddhist now I'm
Jamie gnashing me dick know when people
are saying she like typically I'm sorry
man
when they think they're going to die
Sagara neeterb Armenian pay the Buddha
thinking about the burden will come to
you you're so cool then they'll turn the
top are your minions and then you can
die with a beautiful smile happen okay
alright one more sentence then what do
we call it questions and after that we
have a special section on how to how to
go for shelter okay
damn sak what I'm headed down to atoll
if you take refuge regularly you will
always be born in a good place
okay downs are right you have lots of
chances to practice Dharma you'll be
surrounded by nice people people will
tell the DCI programs in your city every
half hour okay
captain Jang you will meet the blueness
you will have to catching gamboge
epidemic death you'll you will never be
born without taking refuge titled nama
not near cordial same regular Gupta near
the tank our own and then quickly your
experience okay all of this if you just
take refuge where
in the kitchen in the kitchen okay don't
forget all right you got something
special though the whole world thinks
they do this at the temple right and you
understand where that you do it in the
kitchen I like it because you can get
more to eat there then that's a temple
okay we have a few minutes for questions
joel is going to choose not me so if he
doesn't choose here at his phone
I just took refuge issue a practical
question I have a close team member in
my team who it's also these a student
and come to know me before but they you
know that now that there are a lot of
this new age thing and they do a healing
business like they can't see people's
chakras energy and against how you
should do these it should to your
parents well like they tell people nice
thing to do so today you are talking
about not mixing things like science
versus science with needs you know I
have been keeping my mouth shut like
because they also need to do this job to
make money so when I try to do the BCI
project with these team members I see
their world will also affect other team
members because we are on you so I don't
really know what to do should I just
stop them
you know I I don't know what you do and
she's a very close friend yeah it's easy
to get your mind into a bind about it
you know you say should I kick them out
or should I talk to them or should I
shut up and hope they change you know
it's easy to get your mind caught in are
not of choices you know and and the
British method that taking refuge method
is to examine if you're doing anything
like that and stop doing it and then
they were stung because they're coming
from you so you must be doing something
small small thing which is similar in
taste you know you must be doing
something like that
small small because karma grows every
day right so you're not doing what
they're doing but you're doing something
smoked and I don't know what it is but
if you focus your energy not on this
other person and not on the choices you
have to correct them but rather focus on
how you might be doing something similar
in a tiny way they will change
immediately okay it's kind of cool so
don't let your mind get you know should
I get it you know just find it something
similar it's out of you avoid it
slightly and they will stop any other
questions
we have seven more minutes well thank
you for teaching efficient that's beer I
was I didn't see deer here for I've been
coming here for 17 years we just saw
four only
I didn't see were okay no not in the
valley I didn't see in the guy I saw him
over here
well I went to the first retreat in
Guadalajara Monica took me and I didn't
understand anything but now I am very
very happy yes now I understand Lincoln
and he's I know it's going to change my
life
cool thank you very much for me and I
know and thank to all the lovely people
that make it possible you know gravity
and this beautiful Sangha yeah well two
of my closest people in my life like the
term of last year my mother year ago it
was what's a big big and sad
lost and last week my closest friend 32
years of friendship Keith I stood and
both of them died related entanglement
oh oh yeah yeah yeah my mother from
pneumonia and they had to put some
troops at me and Arthur Baker and my
friend he was sedated too
I know that you have to take refuge by
yourself and not know if it's possible
like in that instance to do something
for them they they they are gone now but
if I have the same situation in the
future is there something we can do to
try to do something for them in that
last moment even though they are sedated
or in the other case if they are
awakened and they're in the steps before
the ratification what can we do for them
to try to do something for them to go
through to have another opportunity yeah
good question I had this problem with my
dad he got lung cancer and they did a
terrible operation and maybe you heard
of it it's a way to cut the back and you
break all the ribs and then you try to
cut the cancer out but they broke his
rear as they opened him up in this huh
they said that's not going to work and
they just close it back up quietly you
know and then I start with him while he
was dying for a couple weeks you know
and he was in a lot of pain and he was
taking Brompton solution maybe
cunningness it's morphine heroin it's a
cocktail of heavy drugs and
but we can still talk with me you know
and we say it's very similar to Catholic
faith we believe very it's very very
correct what the Catholic tradition to
confess to a priest just before you die
we believe that's extremely cool idea
and very helpful so if you can get the
person to think about things they did to
hurt people and just in their own heart
they kind of say I'm sorry I did that
so my father in his case in world war ii
he killed many people and he never
talked about it but I knew about it and
then I asked him he's dying you know he
could have died you know in a few days
and I said dad would you do that again
and he said no no I I wouldn't go I
would refuse to go you know I would
never do that again
so then according to a Buddhist belief
he was giving that up he was apologizing
for it in Marin then he died very well
so one thing is important for people who
are dying he wasn't religious
and he didn't I'll tell you a funny
story when he was hunting deer in Utah
and he fell he slipped and he fell on us
rocks and he then he read to the
hospital Mormon hospitals and that they
took an x-ray and the doctor came
innocent they're so lucky you fell death
and hit your ribs because we took an
x-ray and now we know you've encountered
God God's glory you know and my dad was
like why the hell did God give me a
chance to make money anyway
he wasn't religious and he didn't take
any interest in in religion but he in
his final days he apologized for hurting
people and we believe that's a very good
way to die so I think that's one thing
you can do when people are dying is to
try to get them to forgive other people
who hurt them and think about who they
hurt and apologize for it even in their
own mind so that's good if they're
sedated or even after they stop
breathing they can still hear you and in
that case we try to do mantras we do
just some kind of Monday and during that
month has had a way to reach the core of
the brain and help the person even
though they don't think about it so if
your father believed in Hail Marys or
something then you should do Hail Marys
you know quietly in their ear and then
it will bring back all these memories of
of Jesus or things like that so
something they can relate to if they're
Buddhist you can do Oh Moneypenny who if
they're Catholic you can do Hail Marys
whatever they grew up with whisper it in
their ear they can hear that and then
after they die for 49 days they can hear
you we believe they can hear you for 49
days so again it's kind of a cool custom
to just talk to them you know we believe
they can see you but they can't touch
you and it frustrates them it's like
they are separate
by a piece of glass so they can see you
crying they can see you at the funeral
and they're trying to bang on the glass
and and the you don't hear it and they
get really frustrated so if you talk to
them and say and and try to remind them
of good things they did in their life
okay like dad do you remember when you
took me to see my aunt who is sick or
dad to remember when you say that guys
laugh or remind them of good things they
did for you and good for other people so
so even though they're sedated or even
though they're dead and they can still
hear you and so you can still do a lot
you can still do a lot they say you
shouldn't get you shouldn't make loud
noises or you know scream or things like
that should try to be calm makes them
happy okay but that that thing about
talking to people who died is a very
beautiful practice you know I had a
woman whose daughter died very young and
she started to talk to her about 20
years ago she's still doing it she's
still doing it and she's very very happy
she's really happy and she feels like it
helped her daughter in love okay so they
can hear you okay one more question
Joel decides then we go to bed yay
[Music]
thank you John Thank You Krishna you are
teaching and my question is as you
mentioned now is because the Buddha is
very special treasured object so even
though we haven't got the pure
motivation we can plan the goofy to to
get learn yet get enlightened but also
you tell us Buddha is just a little
Jaime
if not a real Captain Jang so I saw the
confusion other kind of information is
the first question and second we will
not haven't got any good at all we treat
everybody like a Buddha like a god we
understanding and emptiness so which is
everybody like a Buddha so we can plan
this kind of degree even though we
haven't got a pure motivation yes like
for example if I choose you like a
Buddha even though I have some selfish
motivation but I serve you I work for
you and I haven't got the good
motivation can I plan to see to get
enlightenment yes it's true there's many
stories of the student who treat their
Lama like a Buddha serve them like a
Buddha and the Lama actually taking
advantage of them Lama just wants money
mama just wants attention or other
things but the student from student side
they treat mama like a Buddha then the
lama go to hell and the Buddha and the
become a Buddha my my question here if I
am as a student sigh I have some kind of
bad motivation yeah opulent
it we are we don't nobody has pure
motivation nobody if you had to
motivation you will be here okay every
person born in this world who is not a
Buddha who is pretending to be a normal
person having a normal person here God
here because they don't have a clear
motivation that the proof that a person
is defected is that they're here all of
us Lama has okay I really good mama has
98 percent bad and normal people have 99
we're all this day only willing come to
this place this is not a good place this
is where they stand all the stupid
students this is a special classroom you
know and Saturday we never have a really
pure motivation it's impossible we can't
have so it's useful as you said to
imagine as many people around you as
Buddha as you can and Tantra is all
about that and that's a big subject in
Tantra so yeah if you even just pretend
the people getting Michael is the last
person in this room who's not a Buddhist
hope all those people come to do that
program they're all Buddha and they just
come there so Geshe Michael will talk
about Buddhism so it will help getting
Michael's
and they're very kind to come and pay
the money and volunteer and rental place
and and it's all just a big shelf and
they're just helping guests Michael will
do what he talks about so we can all
finish and have Brita party he's our
last one left you know that's okay
that's great yeah that's true that's
country yeah
it's called using the result at the top
so you decide everybody's food already
except me and treat them all like Britta
and then you become Bruna cool good
question